Contact

calvinmichel@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/calvindewilde (LinkedIn) github.com (Other)

Top Skills

International Relations

Research

R

Languages

Malay (Limited Working)

Dutch (Elementary)

Indonesian (Native or Bilingual)

Certifications

R Tidyverse Reporting and Analytics
Python for Data Science
Advanced Microsoft Power BI
Data Dashboards in Power BI
R Programming A-Z™: R For Data
Science

Honors-Awards

Travel Awards to present at DevNet conference in Dunedin

New Zealand ASEAN Scholarship Award

Sayembara Novel Dewan Kesenian Jakarta 2006

Khatulistiwa Literary Award

Publications

Minority rights and the Indonesian diaspora

At Long Last, the Rupiah Where It Belongs

Currency reserves: The new balance of power

The Thinker: Behind the Success Is de Nederlandse en Indonesische geschiedenis te verzoenen?

Calvin de Wilde

NZAS | Data Science | #rstats | Aiming to be the Marie Kondo of data Jakarta

Summary

I was an aspiring political analyst who accidentally became a data analyst. This lucky accident has introduced me to the exciting world of big data and analytics and I never looked back ever since.

As a data analyst, I produce insights from various unstructured and structured data source to enable my stakeholders making an informed decision. I have developed an expertise in developing insight for consumer brand campaigns, strategic communication plannings, and crisis communications.

I have over 6 years experience in research and analytics and never tired with my "aha!" moment when discovering something from my data.

I mainly use R, Python, and Power BI to extract, transform, and load (ETL) to transform a messy datasets into a tidy data format that are ready to be deployed for pivot tables and visualizations.

I have handled clients from various sector such as tourism, mining, ICT, development, oil and gas, pulp and paper, healthcare, retail, banking, and pharmaceutical, with an exposure of researching Indonesia, Southeast Asia and Asia Pacific context.

Feel free to connect with me if you want to expand your network or you have a query about my expertise that may be able to help your business.

Data analysis tools:

- Microsoft Excel: vlookup, Pivot Tables, Power Query, and Excel charts
- R (base R, dplyr/tidyverse, & ggplot)
- Python (Pandas, numPy)
- Power BI
- Postgresql

- Data Miners, rvest, twint (Web Scraper)

IDE:

- Rstudio
- Jupyter Notebook
- Spyder

Experience using these service:

- Sysomos/Meltwater Explore
- Talkwalker
- Mention
- Social Bakers
- Sprinklr
- Factiva
- SurveyMonkey
- Iconosquare
- Euromonitor
- Social Studio

Experience

Iris

Senior Data Analyst
October 2018 - Present (1 year 11 months)

Jakarta, Indonesia

As a senior researcher at Iris' Social Media division my main responsibility is to process raw data from our client's digital marketing campaign which is stored in various platforms into digestible reports through visualizations. My tenure at Iris is one of the most important milestone in my career as it pushed me out from my comfort zone and learning data science.

Details are as follows:

- Automation: Extracting data from analytics tools (Meltwater, Sprinklr & Adobe Analytics), validated it to maintain consistency, creating pipelines, automated data cleaning & visualizations, using R/Python, saving 50% working time by eliminating repetitive tasks.
- Dashboard Reporting and Visualization: Pioneered an implementation of digital business dashboard, using Power BI to monitor business analytics of customer's journey such as Engagement Rate (ER), Click-through-rate (CTR),

Conversion Rate (clicks to visits, visits to leads), Cost per Visit (CPV), and Cost per Lead (CPL), easing the access of data across divisions.

 Social media mining: Developing insight over client's digital marketing campaigns' performance through social listening and identifying the current trend of social media contents, enabling the client to maintain brand engagements, positive conversation, customers acquisition, and sales conversion on social media channels.

ETL tools

- Microsoft Excel: Pivot tables & Power Query (ad-hoc data transformation)
- R (data transformation)
- Python (data transformation)
- ggplot & Power BI (visualization).

Data source:

- Meltwater Explore
- Iconosquare
- Social Bakers
- Social Studio
- Adobe Analytics
- Facebook Insight
- Facebook Ad manager
- Facebook Public Posts (via webscrapping)
- Instagram Insight (unstructured)
- Instagram Public Posts (via webscrapping)
- Sprinklr
- eCommerce sales reports
- Media spending reports
- GfK market share reports (unstructured)

Clients:

- Philips Consumer Health
- Corine de Farme
- Nestle
- Diageo

Edelman

Senior Researcher
May 2016 - July 2018 (2 years 3 months)

Jakarta, Indonesia

I was a Senior Researcher at Edelman's Digital Intelligence Center. This position introduced me to the world of big data and analytics in Social Media. I answered questions from the clients such as "what is currently being discussed by people about topic X?", "what is currently trending in social media?", "how do people perceive my brand?".

My role was to provide support data for our client pitch and/or executing research projects from start to finish. This position enabled me to put my background in social scientist into a good use as I did a lot of qualitative and quantitative research during this tenure.

Details are as follows:

- Project management: Managing research projects, budget, performing ad hoc surveys, and literature studies to support new business growth opportunities from Indonesia or other Edelman's offices worldwide
- Research: Designing and executing quantitative and/or qualitative research to drive understanding of targeted consumers or stakeholders' media consumption behavior, brand perception, enabled clients to strategize their communication plans.
- Monitoring: Providing analytics, engagement rate, and performance indicators during campaigns and PR crises, enabled clients understanding their current situation in the social media and hybrid media.

Data source:

- Sysomos (Twitter, News, Blogs, Forum)
- Mention (Facebook)
- Magimetrics (Instagram)
- Euromonitor
- Factiva
- Public policy papers
- Laws
- Market research reports
- Questionnaire
- FGDs
- In-depth interviews

Clients:

- Telkomsel
- Danone

- Asia Pulp and Paper
- Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade of Australia
- Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN)
- Walk Free Foundation
- Traveloka
- FrieslandCampina (Netherlands)
- Starbucks
- APEC (Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation)
- Takeda
- Mondelez
- Bigo
- Meat Livestock Australia
- Amman Minerals
- Fisher Price
- Aminef
- Lippo-Meikarta
- Nissan
- Hewlett-Packard

Media Televisi Indonesia, PT (METRO TV) Senior Researcher April 2015 - April 2016 (1 year 1 month)

Greater Jakarta Area, Indonesia

I was recruited to join the award-winning Mata Najwa talk-show (aired on Metro TV every Wednesday, 20:00). This position allowed me to make use of qualitative research (mostly background check using internal news analytics tool and in-depth interviews) to gain information from our news sources. I also learned how television editorial board planned and executed their idea, and learning the art to communicate public discourse into digestible information to TV audience.

Details are as follows:

- Research: Reported to the senior producers and the vice-chief editor (Najwa Shihab). I was responsible to formulate research various discussion topics and potential invitees through qualitative research, literature reviews, and phone interviews under a tight deadline
- Relationship management: Interviewed and invited public figures such as ministers, legislators, high ranking police, and politicians to participate in the program as news sources and liaised them during on-airs.

Data source:

- Interviews
- News articles
- Laws

Outputs:

- Topic recommendations
- Interview scripts
- Fact-check research compilations

New Zealand Ministry of Foreign Affairs & Trade New Zealand ASEAN Scholarship Awardee February 2013 - February 2015 (2 years 1 month)

Palmerston North

I received a fully funded scholarship to study Master of International Development at Massey University, New Zealand. My research thesis was using a mixed research method, and supervised by Dr. Sharon McLennan.

PT Royston Advisory Indonesia Associate Consultant May 2012 - January 2013 (9 months)

Greater Jakarta Area, Indonesia

During my tenure at Royston, I was responsible to conduct qualitative research and mitigated public crises. I learned how to conduct stakeholder perception mapping and ghost-writing to neutralize public crises. My tenure was cut short as I received a scholarship to study in New Zealand.

Details are as follows:

- Research: Produced qualitative and desk-based research, op-eds, and feature articles to neutralize public crises or influencing public sentiment over certain issues.
- Monitoring: Monitored perception of client's public image from (traditional)
 daily media analysis to achieve the business objectives from the clients such
 as neutralizing negative sentiments during public crises.
- Account management: Maintained relationship with clients and media.

Data Source:

- Interviews
- News articles
- Laws

- Research papers
- Public policy papers

Clients:

- Indonesia Deposit Insurance Corporation (LPS)
- Indosat
- Sampoerna
- Pertamina

HD Asia Advisory Indonesia Researcher January 2011 - April 2012 (1 year 4 months)

January 2011 - April 2012 (1 year 4 month

Greater Jakarta Area, Indonesia

As a researcher, I was responsible to support our firm to execute their main service: stakeholder mapping. This report will be used by our clients who want to navigate the complexity of Indonesia's business and political landscape so they can safeguard their investment in Indonesia.

- Research: Produced stakeholder mapping reports and market research insights on Indonesia's political and business development from highly regulated sectors such as (but not limited to) procurements, mining, aviation, and geothermal.
- Web administration: Administered the firm's Knowledge Centre and disseminated daily newsletters to existing clients.

Data Source:

- Interviews
- News articles
- Laws
- Research papers
- Public policy papers

Clients:

- BSA (Business Software Alliance)
- Nusantara Infrastructure
- the regional government of Papua
- Enterprise Ireland
- Glanbia Nutritionals
- Altobridge
- Tenaris Seamless Pipe Indonesia Jaya

Education

Massey University

Master's of International Development, Development Studies

Massey University

Postgraduate Diploma, Development Studies

Universitas Katolik Parahyangan (UNPAR)

Bachelor's degree, International Relations and Affairs